Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series XXIII: Returning to Chile, 1984-1986
  In the 1970s several thousand Chilean citizens fled their country to escape the dictatorship of Augusto Pinochet. Most of the exiles were either supporters of former president Salvador Allende or activists on the political left who feared abuse under the new government. Exiles were barred from returning for many years, but by 1984 the Chilean government agreed to grant most of the exiles permission to return home. This opening was spurred by international pressure and a domestic campaign to abolish restrictions on exiles.
  Returning to Chile, which documents the return of Chilean political exiles, won a 1986 Silver Toucan Award at the Rio de Janiero International Film Festival.
  Estela Bravo's 1986 documentary Returning to Chile tells the story of Chileans exiles who returned to the country in the mid-1980s. This documentary explores the experience of youth who returned to Chile without their parents after living in exile for many years. Several of the youths featured in the documentary discuss their difficulty adjusting to life in Chile and struggles with identity. A portion of the film focuses on Carlos Godoy Echegoyen, a twenty-three-year-old Socialist who died under torture in a police station in the port of Quintero in February 1985, shortly after returning from exile. Bravo interviews his mother and his sister. It also features scenes in a cemetery at Godoy's grave and the graves of others, including Victor Jara, and Salvador Allende. The film also tells the story of three children from one family whose parents were taken and who must fend for themselves.
  Videos in this series include full-length copies of the documentary with subtitles in English as well as raw footage and interviews. Footage features cemetery scenes, discussions about Carlos Godoy, Chilean religious and social welfare groups, speeches by Pinochet, and other background scenes.
  - Returning to Chile, 1986; cuid18429; 1 Reels (Reel ref2162_01, Reel ref2162_02)
  - Returning to Chile, 1986; 2013.014 (Reel ref2167)
  - Returning to Chile, 1986; cuid791 (Box 96, Dvd ref1302)
    This video contains a full version of short documentary Returning to Chile.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:29:24.
  - Returning to Chile, 1986; cuid18430 (Box 61, Cassette ref1340)
    This is most likely a full-length version of the film Returning to Chile. This film is in Spanish.
  - Returning to Chile, "Cassette #24 DV #9 Final Viejo, Spanish", circa 1984-1986; cuid18431 (Box 45, Cassette ref968)
  - Returning to Chile "English subtitles", circa 1984-1986; cuid18432 (Box 97, Dvd ref834)
    This video features a complete version of the documentary Returning to Chile.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:29:56.
  - Returning to Chile, English, circa 1984-1986; cuid18433 (Box 45, Cassette ref969)
  - "Pinochet Speech", circa 1984-1986; cuid18434 (Box 98, Dvd ref1234)
    This video features a speech by Augusto Pinochet delivered on September 11, the anniversary of the military coup in which he seized power in Chile. In his speech, Pinochet contends that Chile must continue to fight against communism and Marxism. He discusses the history of communism and argues that Chile must stay vigilant because the goal of communism is to take over the world. He contends that his government is protecting democracy, and argues that if critics understood the threat that Chile faced they would know that his actions were correct. The second half of this video features footage of a Cuban dramatic television program filmed by Estela Bravo.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:11.
  - Godoy, Carlos (CH13), circa 1985-1986; cuid18435 (Box 65, Cassette ref1227)
  - Mother of Carlos Godoy: Interview / Protection of Youth Damaged by State of Emergency (PIDEE) (CH14), circa 1985-1986; cuid18436 (Box 98, Dvd ref1228)
    This video begins with an interview with the mother of assassinated political activist Carlos Godoy. Godoy's mother begins by discussing the youth movement in Chile and the reasons Chilean youth have expressed such strong resistance to the Pinochet government. At the time of the interview, which was filmed sometime around 1985, she explains that the children have lived under Pinochet for 12 years and many remember their family members disappearing or going into exile, and cannot see a future for themselves under the current government. She expresses her hope in the community and her faith that the government will eventually change. The video then focuses on news reports and photos of Carols Godoy and his murder. At minute 17:55 the videos changes to an interview with the executive secretary of the foundation Protection of Youth Damaged by State of Emergency (PIDEE), which helped children whose parents had been harmed, detained, or disappeared by the government. She describes the foundation, its goals, and the kind of support it provides to the children whose families were targeted for political reasons.
  - Godoy, Carlos: Interview with Sister (CH18), circa 1985-1986; cuid18437 (Box 98, Dvd ref1253)
    This video features an interview with the sister and mother of murdered Chilean political prisoner Carlos Godoy. The video begins with shots of still images of Godoy, and the interview with his mother and sister begin around minute 3:35. His sister begins by talking about a dove necklace she was wearing, which was made by political prisoners in Santiago. She then discusses how her family moved to Cuba in 1973 following the coup of Augusto Pinochet, and their decision to return to Chile. She describes learning about her brother's death and how the news affected her. She also discusses her hopes of becoming a lawyer or journalist in the future, and her desire to find work that will serve the community.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:32.
  - "Godoy and Sister", circa 1984-1986; cuid18438 (Box 53, Cassette ref1242)
  - "Cemeteries, Godoy, Desolvencias", 1986; cuid18439 (Box 53, Cassette ref1256)
  - "Cemetery (CH19)", 1986; cuid18440 (Box 65, Cassette ref1230)
  - "Cemetery (CH20)", 1986; cuid18441 (Box 97, Dvd ref832)
    This video features footage of families in a cemetery in Chile visiting the graves of their loved ones who had been killed by the Central Nacional de Informaciones (CNI), the Chilean military police. At the beginning of the video police can be see chasing demonstrators outside of the cemetery. The video then features an interview with the mother of Carlos Godoy at his grave. Godoy's mother talks about her son, and his murder, and describes him as emblematic of many Chilean youth. After the interview with Godoy's mother, a man speaks about the memory of Godoy and the importance of continued resistance against Augusto Pinochet in Chile.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:48.
  - "3 Children, Home, Singing (CH22)", circa 1984-1986; cuid18442 (Box 53, Cassette ref1243)
  - "Original, 3 Children, Brother", circa 1984-1986; cuid18443 (Box 54, Cassette ref1249)
  - "3rd Part, Children, School", circa 1984-1986; cuid18444 (Box 54, Cassette ref1247)
  - "3 Children, Street action, Foundation for Social Aid of the Christian Churches (FASIC) ", circa 1984-1986; cuid18445 (Box 65, Cassette ref1223)
  - "FASIC, Venceremos (CH23)", circa 1984-1986; cuid18446 (Box 65, Cassette ref1231)
  - "FASIC, Young People (CH25)", circa 1984-1986; cuid18447 (Box 53, Cassette ref1244)
  - "FASIC, Young People (CH26)", circa 1984-1986; cuid18448 (Box 53, Cassette ref1245)
  - "FASIC, Young People", circa 1984-1986; cuid18449 (Box 98, Dvd ref1254)
    This video features interviews with 4 young Chilean women who returned to Chile after living abroad for many years. The young women describe how life in Chile are different from their lives abroad in France and Canada. Recorded sometime around 1985, the young women discuss how the political culture has changed since the overthrow of president Salvador Allende. One discusses why her family moved to Canada, and her memories of Chile before they left. They also discuss the reasons they decided to return to Chile, and briefly discuss their involvement in youth activist movements.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:28.
  - "PIDEE Cuban Young People", circa 1984-1986; cuid18450 (Box 53, Cassette ref1255)
    Protection of Youth Damaged by State of Emergency (PIDEE) is an organization founded in 1979 and dedicated to healing childhoods shattered by political repression in Chile.
  - "Casa Hogar, PIDEE, Jovenes, Casa Linda", circa 1984-1986; cuid18451 (Box 53, Cassette ref1252)
  - "Peace, Young People (CH15)", circa 1984-1986; cuid18453 (Box 65, Cassette ref1229)
  - "Moneda", circa 1984-1986; cuid18454 (Box 65, Cassette ref1233)
    Palacio de La Moneda is the Chilean presidential palace. Salvador Allende is believed to have committed suicide at La Moneda just prior to its capture by the troops of General Augusto Pinochet (Sep 11,1973).
  - "Mural, Young Children, Church (CH28)", circa 1984-1986; cuid18455 (Box 65, Cassette ref1232)
  - "Mexican Families (CH8)", circa 1984-1986; cuid18456 (Box 53, Cassette ref1239)
  - Returning to Chile "Festivales", circa 1984-1986; cuid18457 (Box 59, Cassette ref1343)
  - Chile - Pinochet (CH5), circa 1984-1986; cuid18458 (Box 53, Cassette ref1251)
  - Chile (CH3), circa 1984-1986; cuid18459 (Box 54, Cassette ref1250)
  - "Pinochet", circa 1984-1986; cuid18460 (Box 53, Cassette ref1246)
  - "Premio Ret a Chile Casa", circa 1984-1986; cuid18461 (Box 57, Cassette ref831)
  - Returning to Chile: Video Clips, undated; TW_TAM_616_ER_11 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_11)
  - "Retornando a Chile", circa 1984-1986; cuid18462 (Box 30, U-matic ref680)
- Series XXIV: Silvio and Pablo in Argentina, 1984
  The documentary Silvio and Pablo in Argentina (1984) shows footage from a concert held in Argentina in 1984 following the country's transition from a military dictatorship to democracy. Silvio Rodriguez and Pablo Milanes, two of Cuba's most popular composer-singer-musicians, organized the concert, which featured some of the best Argentine folk musicians at that time. The documentary shows the enthusiastic response of the Argentine people, as the musicians perform songs that had previously been prohibited in Argentina. This series contains footage of Rodriguez and Milanes in Argentina, as well as some footage of the performers at a concert in the Bronx.
  - Silvio and Pablo Tape 1, 1979-1984; cuid18467 (Box 66, Cassette ref1348)
    This video does not contain footage from the Bravo documentary, but rather footage of the concert itself.
  - Silvio and Pablo Tape 2, 1984; cuid18468 (Box 66, Cassette ref1347)
  - Silvio and Pablo footage, circa 1984; cuid18469 (Box 75, Dvd ref9)
    This tape contains concert footage for first 4.5 minutes. It is followed by unrelated strike footage and an interview with no sound.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:07:50.
  - Footage: Silvio and Pablo in Argentina, 1984; cuid18470 (Box 54, Cassette ref1268)
  - Silvio and Pablo Concert at Hostos Community College (Bronx NY), 1979 February 15; cuid396 (Box 66, Cassette ref1357, Box 96, Dvd ref1357)
    The first 17:30 minutes of this video feature footage of a concert with Cuban folk singers Silvio Rodriguez and Pablo Milanes at Hostos Community College in the Bronx, NY. At minute 17:30 video changes to footage of men in a barbershop.
  - Pablo Milanes at the Karl Marx Theater, undated; cuid18471 (Box 82, Dvd ref645)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:07:00.
  - "Silvio Pablo Argentina", 1984; cuid397 (Box 83, Dvd ref646)
- Series XXV: Those Who Left, 1980-1981
  Those Who Left (Los Que Se Fueron) is a 58-minute documentary released in 1980 about Cubans who left their country after the 1959 revolution to live in the United States. In the documentary, Estela Bravo sheds light on major events in the history of US-Cuba relations including Operation Peter Pan and the Mariel Boatlift. The documentary also features interviews with Cuban Americans in favor of normalizing relations between the United States and Cuba, and others who support the overthrow of the communist government in Cuba. This series contains interviews with individuals featured in the documentary, footage of immigration workers, and incomplete portions of the documentary, and an early version of the film, which was originally called El Dialogo.
  - Those Who Left, 1980; 2016.025 (Reel ref2173)
  - Casal, Lourdes: Interview (also other footage), circa 1980; cuid18472 (Box 83, Dvd ref772)
    Lourdes Casal (1938-1981) was a Cuban poet, sociologist, and activist. She participated in anti-Batista activities in college, but later left Cuba following the revolution. She moved to New York City in 1962, where she attended the New School and received a PhD in Social Psychology. In 1969 she founded the Institute of Cuban Studies. She later returned to Cuba on a number of occasions. On a trip to Cuba in 1979, her health deteriorated and she decided to stay, dying there in 1981.
    The footage begins with Estela Bravo speaking with several people, then some scenes of group dancing, followed at about 00:01:20, by an interview with Lourdes Casal that lasts for about 17 minutes. At the end is a brief black and white clip with Spanish narration at what appears to be an old building with commemorative signs.
  - Casal, Lourdes: Interview (brief), circa 1980; cuid18473 (Box 83, Dvd ref773)
    This brief footage includes about four minutes of an interview with Lourdes Casal. The rest is footage of a march with Estela Bravo speaking to participants. The quality of this footage is poor but it is viewable.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:09:00.
  - Casal, Lourdes: Event (with additional footage), 1980; cuid18474 (Box 83, Dvd ref777)
    The first portion of the tape appears to be the ending of an event honoring Lourdes Casal. The event features a speech about Casal, which is followed by long applause.
    The remainder of the footage is of Estela Bravo and seven young people who represent a group who left Cuba but returned as volunteers for construction projects. Bravo asks a few questions, but mostly the volunteers speak. The sound and image quality are poor, but the footage is viewable.
  - Casal, Lourdes, circa 1980; cuid398 (Box 96, Dvd ref1353)
    This video contains a recording of television program about poet Lourdes Casal created by Los Servicios Informativos de la Televisión Cubana. The program features an interview with Casal about the ways in which her life in Cuban and the United States shaped her politics and her writing career. The program also features footage of her funeral in 1981, and brief interview with mourners talking about her significance as a poet and voice of the people. It includes footage of the event in which she was posthumously awarded the Casa De Las Americas Prize in 1981.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:24:20
  - "Catholic Center", 1980; cuid18485 (Box 60, Cassette ref1359)
  - Cubans in New York: One Year Later, 1981 April-May; cuid18486 (Box 98, Dvd ref1354)
    This video features a complete version of the television program Cubanos en Nueva York: Un Año Después (Cubans in New York: One Year Later). The program was produced for Cuban television by Estela Bravo and contains follow-up interviews with Cubans featured in her documentary Los Que Se Fueron (Those Who Left). Video and audio quality of this recording are very poor.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:30.
  - "Dialogo R1 Those Who Left", circa 1980; cuid18488 (Box 55, Cassette ref1285)
  - "El Dialogo Early Version of Those Who Left", circa 1980; cuid18487 (Box 55, Cassette ref1284)
  - "Escoria" of Union City Interviews, undated; cuid18533 (Box 98, Dvd ref1319)
    This video features black-and-white footage of interviews with Cuban men who left Cuba for the United States. The footage features a series of on-the-street interviews conducted by Estela Bravo in Union City, New Jersey in which she asks the men why they traveled to the United States and what they hoped to find. The majority of the men interviewed were living in the United States for less than a year at the time the interviews were conducted. Many mention that they left Cuba because they did not agree with the communist government. Others explain that they left to find better work and earn money although several mention that they have had a difficult time finding work in the United States. They likewise describe finding it difficult to get adequate housing and access to medical care. One man notes that he has received little support from the existing Cuban community in the US, and has received more support from other immigrant groups including Puerto Ricans and Dominicans. Some of the men mention travelling to the US as part of the Mariel Boatlift. The term "escoria" refers to a statement made by Fidel Castro about Cuban exiles, comparing those who left to escoria (scum).
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:57:25.
  - "Free Havana (Havana Libre) 2 Outside Immigration", circa 1980; cuid18484 (Box 97, Dvd ref798)
    This video begins with an interview with a man who traveled from Miami to Cuba to visit family. In this segment he discusses his impression of the country, which he contrasts with his experience of traveling to Jamaica. The video then changes to on-the-street interviews with Cubans, many of whom express their interest in leaving the country for the United States or Canada. They discuss their reasons for wanting to leave, and what they hope to find outside of Cuba. Many express dissatisfaction with the government and a desire be reunited with family members who have already left Cuba.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:18.
  - "Free Havana (Havana Libre) 1 Common people's opinion", circa 1980; cuid18483 (Box 97, Dvd ref794)
    This videos features several short on-the-street interviews and segments of footage filmed in Havana around 1991. The video begins with a brief interview with a taxi driver about his work and life in Cuba. The segment is followed by a 10-minute interview with a Cuban military leader and a Spaniard living in Cuba named Ignacio "el Gallego" Gonzalez. They talk about three Spaniards, including Gonzalez, who fought for Castro during the Cuban Revolution. The end of the video features on-the-street interviews with individuals in Havana about increased tourism in Cuba, and their opinions about people from the Cuban exile community traveling back to the country.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:04.
  - Footage: Carlos Muniz and interviews with Cuban Immigration staff, circa 1980; cuid18475 (Box 83, Dvd ref789)
    Carlos Muniz Varela (1953-1979), along with his sister, was sent from Cuba to the United States in 1961 as a part of Operation Peter Pan. He later became an outspoken activist in favor of normalization between the United States and Cuba. On April 28, 1979, Muniz was ambushed while driving in San Juan, Puerto Rico and shot several times, most likely by individuals from a counterrevolutionary organization.
    The first eight minutes are old black and white footage telling the story of Carlos Muniz. There is no sound. This is followed by Estela Bravo interviewing a room of women in uniform. They are from the Cuban Immigration Department. The final few minutes appear to involve working men outside. There is a line of people waiting to obtain passports. All of the footage is in Spanish.
  - Footage including events and interviews, 1980; cuid18476 (Box 75, Dvd ref3)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:10:20.
  - Interview with Estela Bravo, circa 1980; TW_TAM_616_ER_14 (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_TAM_616_ER_14)
  - "Mariel Flotilla (Those Who Left)", circa 1980; cuid18490 (Box 36, Cassette ref694)
  - Street Interviews, undated; cuid18770 (Box 25, Cassette 583)
    This video contains street interviews with people in New York City. Estela asks if their lives are better in the United States than in their home countries and if life in the U.S. is what they expected. The interviewees discuss the high cost of living in the U.S. Estela asks if there is equal treatment for Black people and those who speak Spanish. The video ends with cutaways and close-ups of the interviewees.
  - Union City Interviews, circa 1980; cuid403 (Box 66, Cassette ref1360, Box 98, Dvd ref1360)
    This video contains on-the-street interviews with Cuban exiles in Union City, New Jersey. Footage on this tape is duplicated on tape ref1319. Video quality of this tape is poor.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:26.
  - Those Who Left (Los Que Se Fueron), circa 1980; cuid399 (Box 96, Dvd ref1269)
    This is an almost complete full-length version of the documentary feature Those Who Left (Los Que Se Fueron). Video quality of this recording is poor in places and the recording ends abruptly before the credits appear.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 01:02:11.
  - Los Que Se Fueron 1st Part, circa 1980; cuid18478 (Box 55, Cassette ref1282)
  - "Los Que Se Fueron", circa 1980; cuid18480 (Box 57, Cassette ref1303)
  - "Los que se Fueron", circa 1980; cuid18489 (Box 32, U-matic ref474)
  - "Those Who Left #1", circa 1980; cuid18477 (Box 45, Cassette ref980)
  - Those Who Left: Second Part, circa 1980; cuid18479 (Box 97, Dvd ref981)
    This video contains a portion of the documentary Those Who Left. Video quality of this recording is poor and does not include a complete copy of the documentary.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:19:52.
  - "Those Who Left", circa 1980; cuid18481 (Box 55, Cassette ref1277)
  - "Those Who Left Historical Footage with Sound #2", circa 1980; cuid18482 (Box 58, Cassette ref1331)
- Series XXVI: The Three Rafters, 1992
  The 1992 documentary The Three Rafters (Tres Balseros) tells the story of two brothers and their cousin who left Cuba illegally on a raft to Miami. They did not tell anyone about their journey, and after a few months of living in the United States, they asked Cuba's representatives in the United States for permission to return. They were finally able to return to Cuba, and upon their arrival, they share their experiences with relatives who knew nothing of their travels to the United States. Footage from this documentary includes scenes from the three rafters' arrival in Cuba and possibly a full-length copy of the film.
  - Tres Balseros, 1992; cuid400 (Box 31, Cassette ref675, Box 95, Dvd ref675)
    This video contains footage of three Cuban men returning to Cuba and greeting friends at family at an airport. The footage does not contain any audio, but features footage of the men speaking to the camera, and meeting with family after their arrival in Cuba.
  - Three Rafters: Arrival at Airport, 1992; cuid18492 (Box 98, Dvd ref1389)
    This video features footage of the three rafters arriving in Cuba. The footage shows them traveling through customs and then greeting their families. It features brief interviews with the men and their families. One man's mother says she is happy to have her son home because she was afraid he would never return. The men discuss their desire to return to Cuba once they were in the United States and what they hope to do with their futures after they have settled back into life in Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:22:58.
  - "Balseros de Jaime R; more campaign stuff", 1992; cuid18493 (Box 54, Cassette ref1265)
  - "Cojimar, Jaime R, Jose Marti Airport", 1992; cuid18494 (Box 54, Cassette ref1266)
- Series XXVII: Who Am I: The Found Children of Argentina, 2005-2014